Finding Aid for Earl D. Babst papers, 1899-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Earl D. Babst papers 1899-1967
Babst, Earl D., 1870-1967.
85744 Aa 2; Ac
New York attorney and business executive. Papers relating to the publication of his book, Michigan and the Cleveland Era; correspondence concerning University of Michigan alumni affairs and his interest in the Michigan Historical Collections; legal materials and memorabilia concerning work as general counsel of the National Biscuit Company, and as president of the American Sugar Refining Company.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
23 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Mr. Babst and his daughter, Mrs. George P. Bent, II (Donor nos. 700 and 4643 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Earl D. Babst was a nationally known lawyer, industrialist, and businessman, who maintained throughout his life a deep and abiding affection for his alma mater, the University of Michigan. Born July 6, 1870, in Crestline, Ohio, Babst attended Kenyon College, then transferred to the University of Michigan where he received a Bachelor of Philosophy degree in 1893 and a Bachelor of Laws degree in 1894.
Upon graduation, Babst practiced law in Detroit where he also became counsel and associate editor (1894-1902) of The Michigan Farmer, a widely circulated and influential weekly paper. During the 1896 election, he served as secretary of the Michigan Sound Money League, an anti-Bryan, anti-Free Silver organization of businessmen. Two years later, in 1898, he became secretary of the Citizens Committee on Education which initiated a plan for the administration of the public schools of Detroit.
Also in 1898, Babst's career took a new direction when he went to Chicago on a case involving the National Biscuit Company, one of the nation's major food companies that was attempting to market its products in packages identified by national trademarks and promoted by national advertising. Before this time, most food products were sold in bulk containers. The changeover to identifiable packaging involved long and tedious patent and trademark litigation, because each state had its own laws restricting corporations in others states from doing business in their region. Babst was influential in removing these barriers and opening the way for uniformity in the laws regulating the food industry.
In 1902, Babst moved to Chicago with his own law firm - Green, Peters and Babst. In 1906, he went to New York as general counsel and vice president of the National Biscuit Company. In 1915, Babst became president of the American Sugar Refining Company. Here, Babst was primarily responsible for revolutionizing the marketing and packaging of sugar. Until then, sugar was sold to brokers who distributed it to wholesalers and retailers, packed in bags or barrels, and then sold to consumers in paper bags. Upon firsthand investigation, Babst believed the traditional method to be both wasteful and unsanitary. The most efficient and sanitary way to distribute sugar, he felt, was to market it in sealed cartons that would insure full weight and leave it untouched by any hands other than the consumer's.
Although not unchallenged, Babst's viewpoint became established and Babst became a respected voice in New York and Wall Street business circles. During World War I, he represented the United States as a member of the International Sugar Committee that, in cooperation with the United States Food Administration, worked to allocate sugar supplies to the Allies. In 1925, Babst became chairman of the American Sugar Refining Company and its chief executive officer. He served as CEO until 1937, and was chairman until his retirement in 1951. During his career Babst was also director of various New York banks and financial institutions.
During the later part of his life, Babst turned much of his energies to his lifelong love of the University of Michigan. Long active in Alumni Association affairs, Babst had a keen interest in University of Michigan history. As sponsor of the Michigan Historical Collections of the University of Michigan, Babst suggested that a study be conducted of the contributions made during the presidency of Grover Cleveland by U-M alumni and former students. The result was the publication in 1948 of Michigan and the Cleveland Era a book jointly edited by Babst and Collections director Lewis G. Vander Velde.
Earl D. Babst died April 23, 1967 at age 96. In 1903, he had married Alice Edwina Uhl, daughter of Edwin F. Uhl, assistant secretary of state and ambassador to Germany, 1893-1896. Babst was survived by two daughters, Mrs. George H. Parsons and Mrs. George P. Bent 2d.
The Earl D. Babst collection consists of twenty-three linear feet of papers received from Mr. Babst, and after his death, from members of his family, mainly Mrs. George P. Bent 2d. Covering the period 1899-1967, the collection is evenly divided between Babst's University of Michigan activities and his business and legal interests. The series in the collection are: Michigan and the Cleveland Era; University of Michigan activities and alumni affairs; Other activities and interests; American Sugar Refining Company; National Biscuit Company; and Miscellaneous.
The University of Michigan portion of the collection relates primarily to the research for, distribution of, and acknowledgment of the Michigan and the Cleveland Era book, Babst's participation in University of Michigan alumni activities, notably as member of the Senior Advisory Council of the University Club of New York, and his commitment to and generous support of the work of the Michigan Historical Collections.
The portion of the collection relating to Babst's business and legal interests consists of memorabilia and legal documentation accruing as a result of his work with the National Biscuit Company and the American Sugar Refining Company. Also of interest are volumes compiled by Babst relating to a U.S. Senate investigation of sugar shortages in the United States in 1918.
Subjects:
American Anti-Imperialist League.; American Honest-Money League.; American Sugar Refining Company.; Babst, Earl D., 1870-1967.; Lawyers--New York (State)--New York.; Michigan Historical Collections.; National Biscuit Company.; Presidents--United States--Election--1896.; Silver question.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Babst, Earl D., 1870-1967.; Law offices--New York (State)--New York.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--New York (State)--New York.; University of Michigan Club of New York.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Michigan and the Cleveland Era
  - Collected biographical materials used in the preparation of the book
    - Adams, Henry Carter (Box 1)
    - Angell, James B. (Box 1)
    - Candler, Henry E. (Box 1)
    - Cooley, Thomas M. (Box 1)
    - Davis, Cushman K. (Box 1)
    - Dickinson, Donald (Box 1)
    - King, William H. (Box 1)
    - Maxwell, Lawrence (Box 1)
    - Morton, J. Sterling (Box 1)
    - Noble, Alfred (Box 1)
    - Palmer, Thomas Witherell (Box 1)
    - Pennell, Galusha (Box 1)
    - Powers, Orlando Woodworth (Box 1)
    - Shields, John Calhoun (Box 1)
    - Sill, John M. B. (Box 1)
    - Thurber, Henry T. (Box 1)
    - Uhl, Edwin F. (Box 1)
    - Weadock, Thomas A. E. (Box 1)
    - Willits, Edwin (Box 1)
  - Collected material on University of Michigan alumni who served during the Cleveland era
    - In Congress (Box 1)
    - In the Federal judiciary system (Box 1)
    - In the state judiciary system (Box 1)
  - Materials relating to the outline and introduction to the book (Box 1)
  - Reports of Henry Brown and F. Clever Bald (Box 1)
  - Research materials and notes (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book (Box 1)
  - Notebook containing distribution list for the book (Box 1)
  - Notebook containing distribution list for the book (Box 2)
  - Letters of acknowledgment received upon the receipt of the book 1948, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Clippings of reviews (Box 2)
  - Galleys and early printed forms (Box 2)
  - Presentation copy of the book presented to EDB and signed by the co-authors (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1939, 1942-May 1944, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence June 1944-October 1948, 49 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence November 1948-1956, 4 folders (Box 4)
- University of Michigan activities and alumni affairs
  - General papers 1921-1951, 11 folders (Box 4)
  - General papers 1952-1965, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - University Club of New York, Senior Advisory Council
    - Papers re annual luncheon 1939-1951, 13 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1938-1954 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan Club of Detroit
    - Correspondence 1950-1953 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Association reports and lists of directors 1946-1954 (Box 6)
  - Class of 1893 activities
    - List of members (Box 6)
    - Songs (Box 6)
    - Decennial reunion (Box 6)
    - Second Triennial reunion (Box 6)
    - Quindecennial reunion (Box 6)
  - Class of 1896
    - Correspondence and biographical material concerning William McKenzie, a member of the class of 1896 1960 (Box 6)
    - Material concerning reunions of the class of 1896 1946-1949 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Historical Collections 1936-1967, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - William Clements Library 1939-1951 (Box 6)
  - U-M School of Music regarding a memorial to Alice Follett Uhl and Edwina Uhl Babst 1954-1965 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project 1949-1952 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence of A. H. White regarding a memorial to Mortimer Cooley 1943-1946 (Box 6)
  - Papers 1925-1928 on the Michigan League Fund (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1935 concerning the death of Henry Webber (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan memorabilia 1893-1954, 3 volumes (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Club of Detroit: Report on the history of the club 1949 (Box 7)
- Other activities and interests
  - Historical Society of Michigan correspondence and newsletters 1952-1961 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1957-1958 re Martha Bigelow's study of William Alanson Howard (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1949-1954 re Shirley Smith's biography of James B. Angell (Box 8)
  - Printed material and correspondence 1956-1957 re EDB's article, "From Bulk to Package Goods" (Box 8)
  - Articles and correspondence 1946-1948 re trademarks (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Roy Tomlinson 1931-1953 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Henry Bates and John Wilson 1936-1939 (Box 8)
  - National Biscuit Company miscellanea (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous patents and designs (Box 8)
  - Clippings on the Detroit School bill 1898-1899 (Box 8)
  - Addresses, clippings, etc. of EDB (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence of EDB (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous books and pamphlets and unprocessed (Box 8)
- American Sugar Refining Company
  - Letters of congratulation on his appointment as president of the company, A-Z, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia 1915-1918, 4 volumes (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia 1919-1937, 8 volumes (Box 10)
  - Annual reports, bulletins, and miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Sugar Shortage Investigation of the United States Senate 1918
    - Scrapbooks and committee hearings (Box 18)
    - Senate speeches and miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
- National Biscuit Company
  - Newsletters (Box 19)
  - Trademark litigation opinions, etc. (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Record briefs and opinions of litigation (Box 11)
  - Record briefs and opinions of litigation (Box 12)
    continued
  - Record briefs and opinions of litigation (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous
  - Record briefs and opinions from miscellaneous litigation (Box 14)
  - Record briefs and opinions from miscellaneous litigation (Box 15)
  - Record briefs and opinions from miscellaneous litigation (Box 16)
  - American Honest-Money League Pamphlets 1896 (Box 20)
    (Babst was assistant secretary of the Michigan branch of the league)
  - National Business League Pamphlets 1899-1902 (Box 20)
  - Anti-Imperialist League Pamphlets 1898-1899 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook 1898-1899 concerning the Detroit School Bill (concerned with the reorganization of the Detroit Board of Education) (Box 20)
  - Scrapbooks 1894-1900 of the Legal Department column of the Michigan Farmer (Box 20)
    (Babst was editor of the column)
  - Books and articles by or about EDB (Box 21)
  - University of Michigan mementoes 1890s (Box 21)
  - Index of EDB materials given to the Michigan Historical Collections (Box 21)
  - Notebook 1891 of lectures from History VII (16th and 17th century Europe) taught by Professor Richard Hudson (Box 22)
  - Ledger of the Kenyon Athletic Association 1891 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook 1900-1903 of Alice Edwina Uhl (Box 22)
  - Periodical 1920 entitled "The American Sugar Family" (Box 22)
  - Book 1927 Portraits and caricatures by Henry Major (Box 22)
  - Resolution June 21, 1950 from the Board of Directors of the American Sugar Refining Company to EDB (Box 22)
  - Resolution July 6, 1950 of the Board of Directors of the American Sugar Refining Company to EDB (Box 22)
  - Resolution 1953 of the Chase National Bank of New York to EDB (Box 22)
  - Resolution 1961 of the Great American Insurance Company to EDB (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook 1965 entitled, "This and That" containing University of Michigan, Kenyon College, and other printed materials, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Scrapbook 1966 compiled by Harry A. Roberts containing memorabilia from the University of Michigan, the National Biscuit Company, and the American Sugar Refining Company, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Printed travel materials from 1923 world tour
    - China and Japan (Box 23)
    - India, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Java (Box 23)
    - Philippines (Box 23)
    - Hawaii (Box 23)
    - England (Box 23)
  - Printed travel materials from 1925 trip to Europe
    - Germany (Box 23)
    - Strasbourg (Box 23)
    - Italy (Box 23)
  - Photographs (Box 23)
    (see also outsize folder)
  - Diplomas, etc. (Folder 1)